いやぁ
おっとさん おっかさん 助けて
本字幕由诸神字幕组（kamigami.org）制作，仅供交流学习，禁止用于任何商业用途
日听:东吾 king  翻译:念白白 poopy   校对:木落 时间轴:wcaster
Mom! Dad!
Save me!
Tsugaru Province
Father, watch over me.
父上 見ていてください
I, Tsukishima Jinbei,
この月島仁兵衛必ずや 江戸でのお勤めを　立派に果たしてまいります
will succeed in my duties in Edo.
きっと 江戸には 蟲奉行所には
I'm sure that in Edo,
with the Insect Magistrate's Office,
父上のように 強いお人がいる
there are many strong people!
Edo
無涯様
Mugai-sama...
More of them are out tonight.
今日も また 巣食っていやがる
江戸には いったいどんな猛者がいるのか
I can't wait to see the kinds of
strong warriors that are in Edo.
楽しみだ
Like my father!
Here comes
Tsukishima Jinbei!!!
第一話　月島仁兵衛　いざ参る
おお なんと ここが江戸
So this is Edo?!
Good morning!
おはようございます
なんだあれ
拝啓 津軽の父上様
Dear Father, in Tsugaru,
自分は本日より蟲奉行所なるところでお勤めを始めます
today I begin my new job at the
Edo Insect Magistrate's Office.
その蟲奉行所がいかなるところなのかはいまだにわかりません
I'm still not sure what kind of place this is.
ですが 武士たる自分が決めた道
But as a warrior,
I am prepared to do my best,
regardless of the conditions.
どのようなところであっても
粉骨砕身で お勤めにあたる覚悟で 蟲奉行所へ
And I'm on my way there...
But I'm lost!
向かっておりません
父上 江戸の人たちは迷子に冷たいでございます
Father, when you're lost,
the people of Edo are very unkind...
Excuse me...
あの
Yes?
はい
どこか お怪我でも
Are you hurt?
Thank you so much!
かたじけない
しみ入ります　この甘み この優しさ
So sweet! So kind...
申し遅れました
Allow me to introduce myself.
自分は蟲奉行所のお勤めに参った月島仁兵衛と申します
I'm Jinbei and I've come here to work
at the Insect Magistrate's Office!
まぁ 蟲奉行所で
My, the Insect Magistrate's?
はい
Yes.
私は春と申します
My name is Haru.
I work here, at this tea shop.
この茶屋の娘です
なんと
Wow!
どうされました
Is something wrong?
いえ なんでも
No, nothing.
Does your family
お春殿 ご家族で ここを
run this place?
ええ おじいさんと二人で
Yes, my grandfather and I.
二人 ご両親は
Just you two?
What about your parents?
私が幼い頃に亡くなりました
They died when I was young.
あっ そっ それは失礼を
I-I'm sorry...
いえ 江戸では よくある話ですから
Don't be.
It's quite common here, in Edo.
Common?
よくある話
お春 焼けたぞ
Oharu, the meat's done cooking!
は～い
Right!
Thanks for showing me the way, too.
道案内まで かたじけない
いいんです 仁兵衛様はどうして蟲奉行所に
It's fine.
What made you decide to join
the Insect Magistrate's Office?
本当は 津軽にいる父が呼ばれたのです
My father, in Tsugaru, was actually summoned.
しかし 父は動けぬ身
However, my father
cannot travel.
ですから 自分が代わりにお上のお勤めを果たしたいと 父に申し出たのです
So I asked to fulfill my father's duties in his stead.
How wonderful of you.
ご立派ですね
いえ
Not at all.
あっ お春殿こそやはり ご立派
You're even more wonderful!
私 嬉しいんです
I'm very happy.
知ってます 仁兵衛様
Jinbei-sama, do you know how
蟲奉行所がどのようにしてできたのか
the Insect Magistrate's Office came to be?
Suggestion Box
今から１０年前 享保６年に庶民の要求や不満を聞くために
Ten years ago, in the 6th year of the Kyoho era,
suggestion boxes were installed,
as a way for commoners
目安箱が作られました
to reach the government.
江戸のみんなが投書したことで作られたのが
Everyone in Edo wrote letters,
asking for the creation
蟲奉行所です
of an Insect Magistrate's Office.
私もたくさん投書したんです
I wrote many, as well.
私の両親みたいに襲われないよう
To ask the government to
protect us from the insects.
みんなを蟲から守ってくださいって
So others wouldn't be attacked,
as my parents were.
お春殿 あの　その蟲とは いったい
Oharu-dono...
What, exactly, are these "insects"?
あっ お春殿はここに
You stay here!
どうなされた
What's wrong?!
なっ人の　皮
Human skin?
にっ 似ている　あのときの化け物に
I-It looks like that monster from before.
Yarougumo
Prison Spider
やめろ
Stop it!
待つんだ
Wait.
The Insect Magistrates are on their way.
蟲奉行所の者がこちらへ向かっている
私たちに任せるんだ
Leave it to us.
Are you with the Insect Magistrates?
蟲奉行所のお方でしょうか
Matsunohara Kotori
松ノ原小鳥
I'm Matsunohara Kotori,
head of the Insect Magistrates.
蟲奉行所を監督している キミは
And you?
月島仁兵衛と申します
I am Tsukishima Jinbei.
父の代わりに お勤めすべく江戸に参りました
I've come to Edo to serve, in place of my father.
源十郎殿のご子息
Genjuurou-dono's son?
私が呼んだのは津軽藩の剣術指南役である父上だよ
I summoned the master swordsman of
the Tsugaru Province, your father.
父は
My father
can no longer move...
もう 動けないのです
He lost his left leg because of me.
父の左足を 自分が奪ったんです
かつて 自分が藩主様のご子息のお供をしていたときのこと
While traveling with the lord
of the province's son,
自分は出会ったのです
熊が
The bear...
I encountered a monster like this one.
今のような化け物に
しかし 自分は武士の息子でありながら
But despite being the son of a samurai,
藩主様のご子息に恥をかかせてしまいました
I caused the lord's son to shame himself.
（致し方ない）
It can't be helped.
すべては 自分の責任　しかし その責めを
It was all my fault, but...
申し訳ございません
I take full responsibility!
父は 自分の代わりに
Father took the blame.
父上
Father!
自分が ふがいないばかりに父は 左足も地位も出世も
It was my fault,
but my father lost his leg, his position,
and any chance at advancement.
すべて失ったのです
So I want to at least be a strong
samurai he can take pride in,
ですから 自分は せめて父が誇れる強い武士になり
父の代わりにお勤めを果たしたいのです
and perform his duties in his stead!
Please!
どうか
I'm sorry, but fighting insects
like the one you saw
悪いけど 今のように 蟲を相手にするのが蟲奉行所の勤め
is the job of the Insect Magistrates.
Not just anyone can do it.
並の者には務まらないんだよ
Thank you!
ありがとうございます
Eh?
I'll prove to you that I'm not just anyone!
決して 並でないところご覧に入れてみせます
No, that isn't what I meant...
いや そういう意味じゃ
てえへんだ
Trouble!
What's wrong?
どうなされた
It took one of the girls!
女を さらっていきやがったんだ
団子屋の お春ちゃんだよ
Oharu-chan, from the tea stand!
Oharu-dono?
お春殿が  蟲は どこへ
Where did it go?
That way!
あっちだ
Oharu-dono...
お春殿
So others wouldn't be attacked,
as my parents were.
私の両親みたいに襲われないよう
みんなを 蟲から守ってくださいって
No!
いや いやあ
It's quite common here, in Edo.
江戸ではよくある話ですから
It's a Yarougumo.
屋牢蜘蛛の仕業ね
I hate s-spiders.
やっ やだな 蜘蛛なんて
Let's go.
ほら 行くぞ
いや いやあ
No!
No...
いやああ
No!
I'm sorry it took me so long to get here!
助けに来るのが遅くなって 申し訳ございません
Jinbei-sama!
仁兵衛様
It's time.
いくぞ これが江戸での初陣
This is my first fight in Edo.
My name is Tsukishima Jinbei!
月島仁兵衛 参る
Here I come!
Stay calm.
焦るな
Always be ready for a fight!
いつでも 身は戦場に
Always be ready for a fight.
常住戦陣の心構えであれ
そんな単調な技など誰がくらうか
Those tricks won't work on me!
What?
なに
I didn't know there were so many!
これほどの敵が
Oh, no...
しまった
My katana's blade...
刀の刃が
Hydrangea Blossoms!
紫陽花玉
What?
なんと
彼女は火鉢君
That is Hibachi-kun.
The descendant of a ninja clan,
and a whiz with gunpowder.
火薬を得意とする忍者の一族の末裔だよ
Hibachi
Let's go, bugs!
いくぜ 蟲ケラ
Koikawa Shungiku-kun.
恋川春菊君
九十九の人斬りといわれた
Known as the "Killer of 99"...
Repentance Slash!
懺斬り
Koikawa Shungiku
He is a criminal.
罪人さ
I c-can do this...
が 頑張れ 僕
一乃谷天間君は
Ichinotani Tenma-kun comes from
a noble house of onmyodo.
陰陽道を司る御家出身で
僕はできる子
Matsukichi! Tamekichi!
末吉 為吉 急々如律令
Do my bidding!
He uses familiars known as shikigami.
式神を使えるんだ
Full speed ahead!
全力つっぱり
Ichinotani Tenma
They are specialists at insect extermination.
彼らは 蟲退治のスペシャリスト
That is the power of the Insect Magistrates.
これが蟲奉行所の実力さ
How wonderful!
なんと素晴らしい
You may step back.
君はもう下がっていればいい
I cannot.
できません
自分は武士ですから
I am a samurai!
いやああ
Father!
おっとさん　おっかさん
Mother!
助けて
Save me!
I can hear someone crying...
聞こえる　誰かの泣き声が
Facing the enemy, a samurai
must never be afraid.
武士が敵前で臆するなど
なんったる様
Listen, Jinbei.
よいか　仁兵衛
A samurai...
武士たる者
It's my... It's my fault.
僕の　僕のせいで
I'm telling you what it means to be a samurai!
今わしは武士の道を説いている
What will you grow up to be?
貴様は何になる
Someday, I want to be the best
samurai in Japan, just like you!
いつか父上のような　日本一の武士になりたいです
Listen to me, Jinbei...
よいか　仁兵衛
If we are frightened, the people
behind us will be, as well.
我々が臆せば　後ろで守られている者まで恐怖に呑まれてしまう
You must be a shining star
お前の後ろにいる人々が どんな時でも不安に駆られぬように
that washes away fear...
So that those behind you will not be afraid!
お前は人々の不安を消し去る　綺羅星となれ
You can do that, right, Jinbei?
できるよな　仁兵衛
お前はわしと同じ　死ぬまで勝ち続ける武士だろうが
You're like me, a samurai who'll
keep winning until he dies!
はい　父上
Yes, Father!
I failed...
なんたる大失態
自分がいながら　お春殿に不安を与えてしまった
I allowed Oharu-dono to be
frightened in my presence.
お春殿はどうか　ご安心ください
Please don't worry, Oharu-dono...
こんな化け物ごときに　指一本　触れさせませんから
I will not allow these monsters to touch you!
I'll be stronger than anyone.
誰よりも　強く
父上を超えて
Even stronger than my father!
Keep winning until you die!
死ぬまで勝つ
常住戦陣
Always be ready for a fight!
すごい　これほどとは
Amazing.
I'd no idea he was so strong.
仁兵衛様　もう逃げて
Jinbei-sama, run!
力が…
My strength...
I've found my star.
星を　見つけた
小さい頃見上げた夜空の　綺羅星のような星を
Like the shining stars I saw in the
night sky when I was young...
Thank you very much,
ありがとうございます 仁兵衛様
Jinbei-sama.
私　諦めまていました
I'd given up.
こんな死に方　お江戸ではよくあることだと
I told myself that people in Edo
die this way all the time.
父や母のように　私も死ぬのだと
That I was going to die like my parents.
お春殿　ダメです
Oharu-dono, you mustn't do that!
相手が化け物だろうと　理不尽に死んでいい人などいません
No one should have to die that way,
at the hands of a monster!
What are you asking for?
何を願いしているの
蟲から守っていただける日が来ますようにって
That someday, they'll protect us from the insects.
江戸のみんなと　大事なお春もな
Protect everyone in Edo.
And you, too, Oharu.
Your prayer wasn't in vain, Mom and Dad...
おっとさんとおっかさんの願い　無駄じゃなかったよ
此度は助けていただき　ありがとうございました
Thank you for saving me!
名を教えてください
Please tell me your name.
これでも自分は武士の端くれ
I am a samurai.
One day, my blade will repay the
favor your blade has done for me!
剣で受けたこのご恩はいつか　剣で返させてください
自分はまだ半人前ですが
I am not a full-grown warrior yet,
いつかあなたのように強くなって
but I will become strong, like you...
死ぬまで勝ち続ける　強い武士になりますから
A strong samurai who keeps
winning until the day he dies!
自分は月島仁兵衛
I am Tsukishima Jinbei...
無涯さんと話そうだなんて　百年早いのよ
You aren't worthy of speaking to Mugai-sama.
仁兵衛君
Jinbei-kun...
Aren't you coming
来るんだよね　蟲奉行所に
to the Insect Magistrate's Office?
はっ　はい
Y-Yes!
月島仁兵衛
Tsukishima Jinbei...
He might be a good find, Magistrate.
これはよい拾い物をしたかもしれませんよ
Tsukishima Jinbei
蟲奉行様
Shinnakamachi Magistrate's Office
Next Time
What?
なんと
Oharu-dono, bring those over here!
お春殿　それを早くこちらに
それってなんですか
What do you mean by "those"?
胸に隠したその爆弾　今にも爆発しそうじゃないですか
The bombs hidden in your chest
are about to explode!
Jinbei-sama, you pervert!
仁兵衛様のエッチ
Hey!
デボラ
Next time, on Mushibugyou:
次回　蟲奉行
My rival is female ninja Hibachi!
My Rival Is Female Ninja Hibachi
ライバルは女忍者　火鉢